Guide to the Medicine, Health Care, and Nursing in Montana Oral History Project 1989-1992
Montana Historical Society Research Center
- CORRINE DERIANA INTERVIEW, OH 1338; 2 tape(s), Transcript 48 pages
  Corrine Deriana (b. 1924) discusses her early life on the Fort Berthold Indian Reservation, North Dakota; traditional Native American medicine and health care; family life on the reservation; recollections of the 1930s depression and World War II; attending Indian Boarding School in Chemwa, Oregon; employment as a nursing assistant in Portland, Oregon; work as a tray girl and nursing assistant at Montana State Hospitals in Galen and Warm Springs; experiences with patients suffering from tuberculosis, silicosis and other illnesses; experiences with and treatment of mental patients; Native American views on death and dying; employment at St. James Hospital, Butte; becoming a Licensed Practical Nurse; lobbying activities for LPNs in Montana; staff working conditions in nursing homes; credentials and education of nurses; differences between registered nurses and LPNs; later education; the Green Thumb Program; part-time work with the Helena Indian Alliance; and changes observed in nursing and health care during her life. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 6, 1990, Helena, MT.
- GLEN HALVER INTERVIEW, OH 1339; 2 tape(s), Summary 3 pages
  Glen Halver, Glendive, Montana veterinarian (b.1915) discusses Montana veterinary practices; early interest in veterinary medicine; schooling; member of Livestock Sanitary Board; how-to's of setting up a veterinary practice. Interviewed by John Terreo, October 1, 1990, E. Helena, MT.
- NAOMI SUMMERS INTERVIEW, OH 1340; 2 tape(s), Transcript 42 pages
  Naomi Summers (b. 1945) discusses her childhood in Kalispell; home remedies and community health care; Licensed Practical Nurse training and education in Butte under the Manpower Development Training Act; work at the Warm Springs Psychiatric Hospital; the first Cardiac Care Unit at St. Patrick's Hospital, Missoula; employment at Kalispell Regional Hospital; flying with patients on helicopters, and working in the Intensive Care Unit; government regulations on nursing; serving on the State Board of Nursing; difference between Registered Nurses and LPNs; liability insurance; medical costs; health care workers morale; impaired nurses legislation; volunteer emergency medical technicians and transportation; Montana Licensed Practical Nurses Association; and credentialing for LPNs. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 26, 1990, Whitefish, MT.
- RAYMOND AND ANGELINE READ INTERVIEW, OH 1341; 2 tape(s), Summary 11 pages
  Raymond Read discusses his early life in North Dakota; veterinary training at Iowa State University; his veterinary practice at Ronan, Montana from 1941 to 1986; the National Bison Range; recollections as personal veterinarian to the albino buffalo "Big Medicine"; brucellosis vaccinations; and serving on State Board of Veterinarians. Angeline Read discusses her experiences as office manager and bookkeeper for her husband's veterinary practice; treating area animals; and the affects of government regulations and new technologies on veterinary medicine. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 27, 1990, Ronan, MT.
- VERNIE BURNS INTERVIEW, OH 1342; 1 tape(s), Transcript 33 pages
  Vernie Burns (b. 1912) discusses her early life in Tweet, and Polson, Montana; nurse's training and education at Deaconess Hospital in Great Falls during the early 1930s and her recollections of Anna Pearl Sherrick; use of penicillin; affects World War II; pilots ferrying military aircraft to Alaska for eventual use by the Soviet Union; raising a family; working conditions of nurses; surgical and pediatrics nursing; work as public health nurse in Lincoln and Augusta during the 1970s; Hutterites and health care; the clinic in Lincoln and its part-time physicians; history of the clinic emergency medical transportation in the area; Women, Infants, and Children Program (WIC). Interviewed by John Terreo, September 19, 1990, Lincoln, MT.
- JIM OLIVERSON INTERVIEW, OH 1343; Transcript 28 pages
  Jim Oliverson (b. 1938) discusses how he entered the health care profession; his work with the Red Cross in Minneapolis, Minnesota; reasons for relocation to Montana; experiences as Hospital Administrator for St. Luke Community Hospital in Ronan, Montana; difficulties small rural hospitals have in conforming to government regulations; liability insurance; the Hill-Burton program. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 27, 1990, Kalispell, MT.
- TRUDY MALONE INTERVIEW, OH 1344; 3 tape(s), Transcript 51 pages
  Trudy Malone discusses her early life in North Dakota; nurses' training and education at the Mayo Clinic; work as a nurse; raising a family; experiences as U.S. Army nurse in Europe during World War II; work as Director of the State Board of Nursing; training and education of Licensed Practical Nurses (LPNs); liability insurance; changes in nursing education and the attitudes of contemporary nurses; and her two terms as president of the Montana Nurses Association. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 21, 1990, Bigfork, MT.
- STEVE ZWISLER INTERVIEW, OH 1345; 2 tape(s), Transcript 55 pages
  Steven Zwisler (b. 1948) discusses his childhood in Evanston, Illinois; education at St. John's University and University of Utah; choosing a career in health care and relocating to Montana; employment at Holy Cross Hospital, Salt Lake City, Utah as kitchen worker and nurse aide; work as a nurse aide at Clark Fork Valley Hospital, Plains, Montana; service with U.S. Army; views on Vietnam conflict; nurse education at Montana State University; early nursing and obstetric experiences; views on birth and midwifery; liability issues; work as a staff nurse and discharge planner at North Valley Hospital, Whitefish; and emergency medical transportation in the Flathead Valley. Interviewed by John Terreo, October 24, 1990, Whitefish, MT.
- JOHN TERREO INTERVIEW, OH 1346; 1 tape(s), Summary 4 pages
  John Terreo (b. 1954) describes the purchase of the Covenant United Methodist Church, Helena, Montana parsonage by the St. Peter's Hospital Hospice Program; his involvement and observations of that transaction as secretary of the church's administrative board. Interviewed by Janet Sperry, January 24, 1990, Helena, MT.
- JAMES E. MCGREEVY INTERVIEW, OH 1347; 2 tape(s), Transcript 33 pages
  James McGreevy (b. 1916) discusses his early life and education in Iowa City, Iowa; military service with the United States Army in Africa and Europe during World War II; relocation to Montana; experiences with the Murray Clinic in Butte, Montana. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 10, 1991, Butte, MT.
- BRUCE MCINTYRE INTERVIEW, OH 1348; 2 tape(s), Summary 12 pages
  Bruce McIntrye discusses his family; early life in St. John, Washington; his father's medical practice; his own medical education and internship; medical practice in Whitefish, Montana; experiences as public health officer for Whitefish and Flathead County; the 1964 flood; operation of satellite office in Eureka, Montana; family planning; illegal abortions; and legislation affecting public health. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 27, 1991, Lakeside, MT.
- MARY MUNGER INTERVIEW, OH 1349; 2 tape(s), Transcript 54 pages
  Mary Munger (b. c. 1943) discusses her parents' immigration from Canada to Butte; life in Butte; home medical remedies; scarlet fever; nurses training at St. James Hospital, Butte; working in the emergency room treating injured miners; psychiatric nurses' training at Warm Springs; the Cadet Nurse Corps during World War II; the Bolton Bill; the State Health Department in Helena; preventative medicine; physician attitudes toward nurses; Montana Nurses Association; credentialing Registered Nurses (RNs) and licensing Licensed Practical Nurses (LPNs); working as Lake County Public Health Nurse; attitudes toward Health Professionals; Ethel Mitchell, Agnes Pauline, Muriel Lewis; the Perand Bill and National Health Insurance; and salaries, labor problems and negotiations. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 23, 1991, Helena, MT.
- DONALD L. GILLESPIE INTERVIEW, OH 1350; 1 tape(s), Summary 3 pages
  Donald Gillespie (b. 1907) discusses his family and early life in Minnesota; becoming a physician; first pediatrician to practice in Butte; the Murray Clinic, Silverbow County Hospital and Anaconda Mining Company; house calls; infectious diseases; traveling clinics; medical care in Butte during World War II; and liability insurance and health care costs. Interviewed by James McGreevy, M.D., May 5, 1990, Butte, MT.
- DOLLY BROWDER INTERVIEW, OH 1351; 3 tape(s), No inventory
  Dolly Browder discusses family attitudes on health care; health care as a child; distance to nearest medical facility; early obstetrics; influences on becoming a midwife and associated legalities. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 28, 1990, Missoula, MT.
- STELLA "SUNNY" PETERS INTERVIEW, OH 1352; 3 tape(s), Transcript 63 pages
  Stella "Sunny" Peters, a Lame Deer, Montana resident discusses her experiences as a nursing student in Miles City during the 1930s and later as a Registered Nurse on the Cheyenne Reservation. [See also OH 495]. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 6, 1992, Lame Deer, MT.
- JIM OLIVERSON INTERVIEW, OH 1428; Transcript 37 pages
  Jim Oliverson (b. 1938) continued to discuss his career in the health care profession; his experiences at St. Luke Community Hospital in Ronan, as hospital administrator; and the Hill-Burton program. [This is a follow-up interview to OH 1343]. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 27, 1990, Kalispell, MT.
- MARY MUNGER INTERVIEW, OH 1511; 2 tape(s), Transcript 59 pages
  Mary Munger discusses technological changes in nursing, the American Medical Association, and various nursing organizations; labor contract negotiations and collective bargaining; the Northern Pacific Beneficial Association; her work as Executive Secretary of Montana Nurses Association; professional nursing standards; legislation; Medicaid and Medicare; the Montana Hospital Association; Charles Huppe, Allen Donahue, Lee Metcalf, Dorothy Bradley, and John Anderson; the American Nurses Association; illegal abortions; and her work as a nursing instructor at Carroll College and as state chair of International Women's Year committee. Interviewed by John Terreo, May 13, 1992, Helena, Mont.